Register of the Sergeĭ Dmitrievich Botkin Papers, 1917-1935
Hoover Institution Archives
Sergeĭ Dmitrievich Botkin (Serge Botkine) Papers,
1917-1935
30011
Botkin, Sergeĭ Dmitrievich, 1869-1945.
11 manuscript boxes (4.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs, correspondence, reports, memoranda, interview summaries, notes, and printed matter, relating to Russian emigres in Berlin, elsewhere in Germany, and in other European countries, after the Russian Revolution; and to the claim of one Anastasiia Nikolaevna Chaikovskaia to be Grand Duchess Anastasia of Russia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1930.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (14 reels).
Access Points
Anastasiia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess of Russia; Refugees.; Russians--Germany; Berlin (Germany); Germany; Soviet Union; Russia; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921; Romanov, House of
Scope and Content of Collection
Memoirs, correspondence, reports, memoranda, interview summaries, notes, and printed matter, relating to Russian emigres in Berlin, elsewhere in Germany, and in other European countries, after the Russian Revolution; and to the claim of one Anastasiia Nikolaevna Chaikovskaia to be Grand Duchess Anastasia of Russia.
Container List
- REMINISCENCES, n.d. (Box 1)
  Handwritten copy of S. Botkine's reminiscences
  - Handwritten copy of S. Botkine's reminiscences (Box 1., Folder 1)
- FORMER RUSSIAN DIPLOMATIC REPRESENTATIVES, 1921-1925. (Boxes 1-2)
  Reports from former Russian diplomatic representatives in various countries to the Senior Diplomatic Representative in Paris. Reports to Senior Diplomatic Representative in Paris from:
  - Athens, 1923-24 (Box 1., Folder 2)
  - Batavia, 1922 (Folder 3)
  - Belgrade, 1923-25 (Folder 4)
  - Berne, 1922-24 (Folder 5)
  - Budapest, 1924 (Folder 6)
  - Constantinople, 1923-24 (Folder 7)
  - Copenhagen, 1923-24 (Folder 8)
  - Egypt, 1923 (Folder 9)
  - Hague, The, 1923-24, 1925 (Folder 10)
  - Helsingfors, 1923-24 (Folder 11)
  - League of Nations, 1922-24 (Folder 12)
  - London
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 13)
    - 1923
      - January-April (Folder 14)
      - May-August (Folder 15)
      - September-December (Folder 16)
    - 1924
      - January-March (Folder 17)
      - April-December (Box 2., Folder 1)
    - 1925 (Folder 2)
  - Madrid, 1924 (Folder 3)
  - Oslo, 1923 (Folder 4)
  - Paris, 1923-1925 (Folder 5)
  - Prague, 1923-1924 (Folder 6)
  - Reval, 1922-1924 (Folder 7)
  - Riga, 1922, 1924 (Folder 8)
  - Rome, 1922-1924 (Folder 9)
  - Sofia, 1923, 1925 (Folder 10)
  - Stockholm, 1923-1924 (Folder 11)
  - Tokyo, 1922-1925 (Folder 12)
  - Vatican, The, 1923 (Folder 13)
  - Vienna, 1924 (Folder 14)
  - Warsaw, 1923-1924 (Folder 15)
- Subject File, 1917-1929 (Boxes 2-8)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed matter and published materials. Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Anti-bolshevik propaganda, 1919-1928 (Box 2., Folder 16)
  - Anti-bolshevik russian representatives (Folder 17)
  - Baltic states - Economic conditions, 1919 (Folder 18)
  - Bessarabia - Events and conditions, 1917-1919 (Folder 19)
  - Finland - Foreign relations - Russia, 1919 (Folder 20)
  - Germany
    - Economic conditions, 1922-1924 (Box 3., Folder 1)
    - Events and conditions, 1925-1930 (Folder 2)
  - Poland - Foreign policy and nationalities, 1919 (Folder 3)
  - Russia
    - History, 1919-1923 (Folder 4)
    - Nationalities, 1918-1919 (Folder 5)
  - Russians in foreign countries
    - General, 1923-1924 (Folder 6)
    - Bulgaria, Russko-Bolgarskii Kul'turno-Blagotvoritel'nyi Komitet, 1925 (Folder 7)
    - China and Mongolia (Folder 8)
    - Commercial and industrial enterprises, 1921 (Folder 9)
    - Education (Folder 10)
    - Prague, Czechoslovakia, 1923-1924 (Box 4., Folder 1)
    - Publications by emigres
      - General
        - 1920-1922 (Folder 2)
        - 1922 (Folder 3)
        - 1923-1929 (Folder 4)
      - Bulletin de la Societe Russe de la Croix Rouge, 1921-1922 (Folder 5)
    - Russian emigre organizations
      - General, printed matter relating to economic and political questions submitted to:
        - Conference of Genoa and League of Nations, 1921-1922 (Folder 6)
        - Foreign governments, 1918-1919 (Folder 7)
      - France
        - Obshchestvo Sluzhashchikh Ministerstva Innostrannykh Del (OSMID), 1921-1924 (Folder 8)
        - Russkii Soedinennyi Klub, Paris, 1925-1929 (Folder 9)
      - Germany
        - General, 1920-1929 (Folder 10)
        - Conferences of Russian social organizations, 1922-28 (Box 5., Folder 1)
        - Obshchestvo Sluzashchikh Ministerstva Innostrannykh Del (OSMID), 1922-1928 (Folder 2)
        - Organizatsiia Zashchity Interesov Russkikh Bezhentsev v Germanii
          - General
            - 1919-1924 (Folder 3)
            - 1924-1930 (Folder 4)
          - Blagotvoritel'nyi Otdel, 1920-1929 (Folder 5)
          - League of Nations, 1923-1929 (Folder 6)
          - Red Cross, 1919-1924 (Folder 7)
        - Russian monarchist group, Reichenhall, 1922 (Folder 8)
        - Russian Red Cross in Germany, 1927-1929 (Folder 9)
        - Russisch-Deutscher Klub, Berlin, 19278-1929 (Folder 10)
        - Russkaia Natsional'naia Molodezh, Berlin, n.d. (Folder 11)
        - Russkii Komitet v Berline
          - General
            - 1919-1920 (Folder 12)
            - 1921 (Folder 13)
          - Blagotvoritel'nyi Otdel, 1919-1920 (Folder 14)
          - Blagotvoritel'nyi Otdel, 1919-1920 (Box 6., Folder 1)
        - Russkoe Blagotvoritel'noe Obshchestvo v Germanii, 1921 (Folder 2)
        - Russkoe Obshchestvennoe Sobranie, Berlin
          - 1919-1920 (Folder 3)
          - 1921 (Folder 4)
        - Soiuz Rossiiskikh Torgovo-Promyshlennykh i Finansovykh Deiatelei v Germanii, 1923-1924 (Folder 5)
        - Staryi Klub, Berlin, 1922-1930 (Folder 6)
      - Rossiiskii Zemsko-Gorodskoi Komitet Pomoshchi Rossiiskim Grazhdanam Zagranitsei, 1922-1929 (Folder 7)
      - Russian Red Cross in Europe, 1920-1922 (Folder 8)
      - Russkie Iuristy Zagranitsei, 1922 (Folder 9)
      - Russkoe Natsional'noe Studencheskoe Bratstvo, 1922 (Box 7., Folder 1)
      - Sviatoe Vladimirskoe Bratstvo, 1920-1930 (Folder 2)
      - Vserossiiskii Zemskii Souiz, 1922-1924 (Folder 3)
    - Russian Orthodox Church, Berlin, 1928 (Folder 4)
  - Soviet Union - Events and conditions
    - 1924
      - February-June (Folder 5)
      - October-December (Folder 6)
    - 1925
      - January-June (Folder 7)
      - July-August (Folder 8)
      - September-December (Folder 9)
    - 1926
      - January-March (Box 8., Folder 1)
      - April-December (Folder 2)
    - 1927 (Folder 3)
    - 1928 (Folder 4-5)
- CASE OF A. N. CHAIKOVSKII, 1925-1935 (Boxes 8-11)
  Correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, writings, printed matter and clippings relating to the investigation of allegations by A. N. Chaikovskii claiming to be Grand Duchess Anastasia Romanoff. Arranged by last names of individuals and by subject
  - General, background information and explanatory notes (Box 8., Folder 6-7)
  - Andrew, Grand Duke, correspondence with Baron Osten-Sacken, 1927 (Folder 8)
  - Bohnhoeffer, Dr.
    - Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Folder 9)
    - Report, March 8, 1926 (Folder 10)
  - Botkine, Gleb, correspondence
    - Kseniia Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess, 1928 (Folder 11)
    - Mel'nik, Tat'iana, 1927 (Folder 12)
  - Botkine, Serge
    - Correspondence
      - Andrew, Grand Duke
        - 1926-1930 (Folder 13)
        - 1926-1932 (Folder 14)
      - Botkina, Nina, excerpts from letters, 1926-1931 (Box 9., Folder 1)
      - Botkine, Gleb, 1927-1928 (Folder 2)
      - Debagorii, Maria, 1926-1927 (Folder 3)
      - Fallows, Edward H., 1928-1935 (Folder 4)
      - Girs, Mikhail, 1926-1931 (Folder 5)
      - Gorlov, Vladimir M., 1927 (Folder 6)
      - Kaznakov, Aleksandr N., 1926 (Folder 7)
      - Kryzhanovskii, Sergei E., 1926 (Folder 8)
      - Kseniia Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess, 1927-1928 (Folder 9)
      - Kuegelgen, Paul von, 1928 (Folder 10)
      - Kutepov, Aleksandr P., 1926 (Folder 11)
      - Lampe, Aleksandr A. fon, 1926-1927 (Folder 12)
      - Leuchtenberg, Georgii N., 1926-1928 (Folder 13)
      - Magnus, Julius, 1932 (Folder 14)
      - Mel'nik, Tat'iana, 1926-1927 (Folder 15-16)
      - Newspaper editors, 1928 (Folder 17)
      - Orlov, Nikolai V., 1926 (Folder 18)
      - Orlov, Vladimir G., 1927 (Folder 19)
      - Osten-Sacken, Baron, 1926-1932 (Folder 20)
      - Poklevskii-Kozel, Stanislav, 1926 (Folder 21)
      - Pushkina, V., 1926 (Folder 22)
      - Rathlef-Keilmann, Harriet von, 1926 (Folder 23)
      - Shebeko, Nikolai, 1926-1927 (Folder 24)
      - Shikhmatov, Aleksei A., 1927 (Folder 25)
      - Urvantsov, Lev, 1926-1927 (Folder 26)
      - Zahle, H., 1926-1928 (Folder 27)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 28)
    - Statement, March 1929 (Folder 29)
  - Dassel, Feliz, articles in the German press, 1927 (Folder 30)
  - Debagorii, Maria, correspondence
    - Andrew, Grand Duke, 1927-1928 (Folder 31)
    - Leuchtenberg, Georgii N., 1927-1928 (Folder 32)
    - Osten-Sacken, Baron, 1926-1927 (Folder 33)
    - Witte, G., 1927 (Folder 34)
    - Zahle, H., n.d. (Folder 35)
  - Eitel, Th., correspondence, 1926-1927 (Folder 36)
  - Gilliard, Pierre, correspondence
    - Gibbes, Mr., 1926 (Folder 37)
    - Kokovtsev, Count, 1926 (Folder 38)
    - Mel'nik, Tat'iana, 1926 (Folder 39)
    - Orlov, Nikolai, 1926 (Folder 40)
    - Ratlef, Mrs., 1925-1926 (Folder 41)
    - Zahle, H., 1926 (Folder 42)
  - Guenther-Geffers, Frau, reports, 1926-1927 (Folder 43)
  - Koehler, Egon, letter to Mrs. Serge Botkine, March 3, 1926 (Folder 44)
  - Lavington, F., statement, November 6, 1927 (Box 10., Folder 1)
  - Lawsuits in the German press relating to the A. N. Chaikovskii case
    - General, 1927-1931 (Folder 2)
    - Berliner Nachtausgabe, 1927-1928 (Folder 3)
    - Der Jungdeutscher, 1927 (Folder 4)
  - Leuchtenberg, Georgii N., correspondence
    - Osten-Sacken, Baron, 1927 (Folder 5)
    - Witte, Georgii G., 1927 (Folder 6)
    - Zahle, H., 1927 (Folder 7)
  - Mel'nik, Tat'iana
    - Correspondence
      - Andrew, Grand Duke, 1926-1929 (Folder 8)
      - Baumgarten, M., 1927 (Folder 9)
      - Botkina, Nina, 1926-1927 (Folder 10)
      - Chaikovskii, A. N., 1926 (Folder 11)
      - Debagorii, Maria, 1927-1928 (Folder 12)
      - Doctors and nurses having cared for A. N. Chaikovskii, 1926-1927 (Folder 13)
      - Fallows, Edward H., 1929 (Folder 14)
      - Gilliard, Pierre, 1926 (Folder 15)
      - Leuchtenberg, Georgii N., 1927-1928 (Folder 16)
      - Olga Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess, 1926 (Folder 17)
      - Osten-Sacken, Baron, 1926-1927 (Folder 18)
      - Rathlef-Keilmann, Harriet von, 1926 (Folder 19)
      - Zahle, H., 1926-1927 (Folder 20)
    - Diary, August-September 1926 (Folder 21)
    - Notes regarding A. N. Chaikovskii, 1927-1928 (Folder 22)
  - Nieper, F., letter and report, 1931 (Folder 23)
  - Nobel, Dr., report, April 21, 1926 (Folder 24)
  - Nolde, Elsa, correspondence, 1932 (Folder 25)
  - Olga Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess, correspondence
    - Mel'nik, Tat'iana, 1926 (Folder 26)
    - Zahle, H., 1925 (Folder 27)
  - Osten-Sacken, Baron
    - Correspondence with Felix Dassel, 1927-1928 (Folder 28)
    - Statements regarding A. N. Chaikovskii, 1926 (Folder 29)
  - Press coverage (Folder 30)
  - Rathlef-Keilmann, Harriet von
    - Articles in the German press, 1927 (Box 11., Folder 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Hochleitner, Alois, 1927-1928 (Folder 2)
      - Jakubowsky, G., 1927 (Folder 3)
      - Osten-Sacken, Baron, 1926 (Folder 4)
      - Zahle, Herluf, 1926 (Folder 5)
    - Manuscript of a book on A. N. Chaikovskii (Folder 6)
    - Notes regarding A. N. Chaikovskii, n.d. (Folder 7)
  - Rudnev, Sergei M., notes, n.d. (Folder 8)
  - Saathoff, Dr., correspondence, 1926-1927 (Folder 9)
  - Spindler, Gertha O.
    - Correspondence
      - Botkine, Serge, 1926-1927 (Folder 10)
      - Zahle, H., 1926 (Folder 11)
    - Report on trip to Rumania, 1926 (Folder 23)
  - Urvantsov, Lev, correspondence
    - Ratlef, Garriet fon, 1926 (Folder 13)
    - Spindler, Gertha, 1926 (Folder 14)
  - Wasserschleben, Agnes, correspondence, 1926-1928 (Folder 15)
  - Zahle, H., correspondence with Baron Osten-Sacken, 192 (Folder 16)